All right everybody, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is ninety-nine,
צדיק ט'. Tzadik Tet.
And we are beginning at the very top of צדיק ט' עמוד
א'. Tzadik Tet Amud Aleph. And the question here is, the גמרא
Gemara is actually getting into some interesting questions of what are the
parameters under which a שליח, shaliach, an agent, is considered to be
operating under the terms of his agency and to what degree has
he gone rogue and is considered to act independently. And the relevance
of course is that if he engages in certain transactions and deals,
then is he operating as the agent and those deals are binding
or has he been operating as himself and therefore they are not
binding if he's trying to buy or sell the person who appointed
him the property of for or of the person who appointed him.
So that's and the specific question is when the person tells him,
"do X, go buy a hundred dollars worth of something" and he
buys fifty, or "go buy fifty dollars worth of something" and he
buys a hundred, or if he tells him to sell something of
that nature. So on any changes is do we say, "well, at
least there's a part of overlap where he's working as an agent"
or do we say "he changed and therefore he's not working as
an agent at all"?
Another case in which this is relevant that the גמרא Gemara actually
draws in as a good way of testing it, as an example,
is the issues of מעילה. Meila. When you tell somebody to go
ahead and to spend something, give something, and it turns out to
be הקדש, hekdesh, turns out to be sanctified, and you're not aware
and he's not aware, then this is one area in הלכה Halacha
where we say יש שליח לדבר עבירה yesh shaliach l'dvar aveira that
if he goes ahead and does it and he's unwitting and you're
unwitting and so on, then actually you, the one who sent him,
are the one who has done מעילה. Meila. So therefore, under circumstances
where he changes what you said, whether you've done מעילה, Meila, you've
both done מעילה, Meila, etc., will reflect on whether he's working under
your agency or working independently. So that's the issue and that's what's
going to continue today in the different variations. And the one case
specifically that we had started with yesterday was when you told him
to go ahead and buy for you a field worth fifty, a
fifty-acre field and he went ahead and he bought a hundred-acre field.
Is he considered to have acted on your behalf for perhaps half
of that field and the other half independent, or is the whole
purchase considered to be independent?
Yes. "There's a לשון lashon in קידושין Kiddushin where he sends the
שליח, shaliach, says for it to be מקדש mekadesh a woman for
a certain amount of money and then the מחלוקת machlokes is whether
he meant in general or a specified amount, is that brought in
here also this
סוגיא sugya is there also?" "Yeah, you're right, there's definitely סוגיות sugyas
in קידושין Kiddushin that are definitely similar about
this. That is correct. That is correct. And they're a bit scattered.
So that is correct. Okay, so actually, I'm sorry, I misstated it.
The discussion yesterday was not about buying, it was about selling. Presumably
it would be the same, but one could make differences. So you
told him to sell to give a sell field of what do
you call it, of like a half an acre and he sold
a field of an acre.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara turns to the case of our משנה,
Mishna, which was the woman who is seen of, nobody appointed her
a שליח, shaliach, but she's implicitly, since she has the right to
sell from the estate in order to pay off her כתובה, ketubah,
she's seen as a type of a שליח shaliach of the estate
or שליח shaliach of the orphans, even though they might not want
her to be doing it. But anyway, she's sort of court-appointed or
rabbinically appointed in that capacity. And the case in the משנה Mishna
was where she sold off something worth 125 for 100. And it
says that the sale is binding. So it says you see that
she basically, and it assumes that what we're talking about is, excuse
me, I misstated it. It assumes that what we're talking about is
that she sold something worth
125 for 125, but she wasn't entitled to sell that much because
she only had an outstanding debt of 100. שמכרה שוה מנה ופרוטה
במנה. sh'makhra shaveh maneh u'peruta b'maneh.
I'm sorry,
I'm sorry, you're right.
It's not binding. Sorry, sorry. Okay, I'm getting ahead of myself. Okay,
yes, thank you. So it is not binding. And what's the case?
The גמרא Gemara assumed that the case was that she sold something
worth 125 for 125, but she wasn't entitled to sell that much
because she only had an outstanding debt of 100. So that and
it says, thank you Michael, you're correct, it says that it's void.
So that proves she was only have the license, she was only
a שליח shaliach for 100. She sold 125, and we say the
whole thing she did is void, so that's not just that, not
just the extra 25 is void. So the גמרא Gemara says that
seems to be a proof for our discussion that the whole thing
you're operating independently. And the גמרא Gemara says no, let's look at
the last line of צדיק ט' עמוד א'. Tzadik Tet Amud Aleph.
אמר רב הונא בריה דרב נתן לא בדאזיל. Amar Rav Huna brei
d'Rav Natan lo b'daozil.
It's not that she sold 125 for 125." she sold a hundred
and twenty-five and the whole problem was that she sold more. The
problem was she sold a hundred and twenty-five for a hundred. Okay,
so she sold it for less than it was worth. And that's
the problem, not that she sold too much land, but she sold
the land for less than it was worth. Therefore, therefore it's void
because she's not operating, she's operating against the interests of the heir,
the owner. She has no right, she has no right to sell
it for less than it is worth, and therefore it's automatically void,
and that's why, not because she stepped outside of the bounds of
her agency. Okay, so let's take a look now at the top
of צח עמוד א. tzadi chet amud aleph. So the גמרא Gemara
says, האי מדסיפא בדאוזיל הרי רישא בדלא אוזיל. Hai mid'seifa bid'ozil ha'rei
reisha bid'lo ozil. One minute, the end of the משנה Mishnah is
clearly talking about a case where she undersold it. So therefore the
beginning doesn't need to be talking about that case, it must be
talking about where she sold too much land, but not that she
undersold it. How do you know that? דקתני סיפא, D'katni seifa, here's
the case in the end. היתה כתובתה ארבע מאות זוז, Hayta ketuvatah
arba me'ot zuz, the כתובה ketuvah was four hundred זוז, zuz, ומכרה
לזה במנה ולזה במנה, umachra l'zeh b'maneh ul'zeh b'maneh, she sold for,
to get guys one, two and three for a hundred, a piece
of land for a hundred, and she had a hundred dollars left
of her כתובה, ketuvah, ולאחרון מכרה שוה מנה ודינר במנה, ul'acharon machra
shaveh maneh v'dinar b'maneh, so to the last guy she sold a
piece of land, she sold שוה מנה ודינר במנה, shaveh maneh v'dinar
b'maneh, so she sold one, a land worth a hundred and twenty-five
for a hundred. So that's explicitly a case of underselling, and it
says של אחרון מכרה בטל, shel acharon machrah batel, last one it's
void, ושל כולם מכרן קיים, v'shel kulam machran kayam, the other ones
it is binding.
So there it's clear that when she undersells it, when she sells
it for less than its value, it is void. And therefore, when
we talked about selling a hundred and twenty-five in the first case
in the משנה, Mishnah, we didn't need to be talking about underselling
it, so we presumably we're talking about selling a hundred and twenty-five
for a hundred and twenty-five, and the point of the משנה Mishnah
that it's void is because she steps outside of the bounds of
her agency. Yes.
Why is the תלמוד Talmud introduce the whole issue or concept of
שליח shaliach here if it's about a person seizing property that's liened
for, to pay a debt? In other words, you don't need to
be a שליח.
shaliach. Right. So this is not a debtor, this is not a
debtor that comes and seizes the property and then בית דין Beit
Din assess it and they walk away with that piece of land
because they've now exercised their mortgage. This is a woman who is,
you're right, I mean it's funny that she's given this latitude, but
she doesn't, if she was going to seize it then בית דין
Beit Din would assess the land and she would just take the
land. So she could do that, you're right. But the גמרא Gemara
is conceptualizing it that she is, you're right, that she is like,
what do you call it? That she is, it says that she
has the right to sell
שלא בבית דין, shelo b'Beit Din, that's not something you say about
a creditor. They have a right to sell, no, they actually seize
the property through the court.
So the תלמוד Talmud is actually saying when a woman's in this
position she could act as a creditor
or she can act as an emissary. Right, the reason that she's
seen here as a שליח shaliach is because mostly we're talking about
the issue of מזונות mezonot and that's going to be an ongoing
process. So like, you know, you don't go to the court to
seize property unless it's like a one debt and you're going to
collect the whole thing. Here it might be every six months, you
know, she wants to sell a little bit more to pay for
the food. Okay. But yes, that is interesting, but the גמרא, Gemara,
it's clear from the משנה Mishnah that we, I mean a, the
language of מוכרת שלא בבית דין, mocheret shelo b'Beit Din, and also
for example, if she sold a field, a piece worth a hundred
for two hundred, it's considered that she's paid off. If I go
ahead and I seize a piece of property of yours because you
had, I had a mortgage on it and it was a debt
and it was a hundred, then I went out and turned around
and sold it and made a profit, that wouldn't pay off your
debt to me. Right, you know, you still owe me the rest
of the money. So it's very clear that she's acting here, you
know, she's empowered to do this, the proceeds go to her pay
off the debt, she's not seizing the property for her debt. The
fact though what's not explicit but the גמרא Gemara assumes is if
she's empowered to do it, she's acting as a שליח shaliach for
the heirs. That's how the גמרא Gemara conceptualizes. You could have said
she's acting, I don't know, as a שליח shaliach of the court
or something.
Yes. But wouldn't it be the case where if she didn't undersell
the property but she sold say more than what was required that
she could give the extra amount back to the heirs?
No, the משנה Mishnah said that even if she offers to give
the extra amount back to the heirs it doesn't work. Oh, okay.
Okay. So now, alright, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. So it
says, okay, so we've got in the end that if she sells
something for a hundred and twenty-five for a hundred, it's void, so
the, I'm sorry, yes, so if she undersold it. So the first
case about a hundred and twenty-five must be a case where she
didn't undersell it but she sold too much and that's why it's
void. I'm going to have to do something about the temperature in
this room. Alright, anyway, yeah, so just the
air in the whole building.
I
don't know to what extent.
But anyway,
everybody's complained in the winter, all winter.
Alright, moving on. Alright, alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, לא, רישא וסיפא בדאוזיל. Lo,
reisha v'seifa bid'ozil.
The
beginning and the end of the משנה Mishnah are both cases where
she undersold it. So why do you need to tell me two
cases? וסיפא קא משמע לן, v'seifa ka mashma lan, טעמא דאוזיל ביתמי.
tama d'ozil b'yatmei.
So the end comes to teach us the reason where she undersold
it regarding orphans. And it's telling you that the reason it's void
is because she undersold and it was a time and the extra
money would have gone to the heirs. אבל בדידה, Aval b'dide, if
she undersold and is still selling it out of her own, מכר
קיים, mecher kayyam,
it's valid. What does that mean? It means remember the first case
of the משנה, Mishnah, which is then the גמרא Gemara is going
to ask, which will be that it's redundant, but the first case
of the משנה Mishnah is she sold a field worth 200 for
100. Okay, we don't say it's void. We say, okay, so take
that whole 200 it was worth and and your כתובה Kesubah is
paid off. You basically, you know, you hurt yourself by underselling it.
So that fact that you undersold it, you're going to take that
hit. Okay, and therefore you're going to... now you have to know
that by the way there's no הלכה halacha of אונאה ona'ah by
קרקע. karka. By chattel, if it's undersold or oversold and if the
price exceeds significantly the going rate, then it's void because it was
an unfair transaction. But by land, because the value of real estate
is so unfixed, there's no concept of under or overselling in terms
of voiding it on the account of that. Here, if it's going
to be voided, it'll only be because she did not, she was
not operating appropriately as an agent of the יתמי. yatme. So here,
but now, if she basically took the piece of land worth 200
and sold it for 100, they can say, okay, that's valid, it's
not going to be void. Ah, you hurt our interest? You didn't
hurt our interest, you hurt your own interest. You have to lose,
take the loss, because if that was worth 200 and you should
have gotten 200, then we'll consider it like the debt's been paid.
That's what the beginning of the משנה Mishnah says. So the גמרא
Gemara said, okay, well that's what the end is teaching you, because
the end gives you a case where there was only 100 left
of the debt and she sold up a land worth of 125
for 100. In that case, she can't take the hit, right? Because
that extra 25 is not there for her, her debt was only
100. There's no hit for her to take. So in that case
where it was undersold and she can't take the loss, then the
sale is void. So that's why it's telling you that case. But
let's just finish this thought, hold on. So it says like this,
it says הא קמשמע לן, ha kamashma lan, it's teaching you טעמא
דאוזיה בדיתמי. ta'ama d'ozya b'deyatme. The reason it's void is because she
undersold it and it's the orphans, the heirs, that are taking the
hit. אבל בדידה, Aval b'dide, if she would take the hit, that
the difference would still be able to go towards her debt, so
מכר קיים, mecher kayyam, it would be valid and she would have
to take the hit. גמרא Gemara says הא דרישא שמעת מינה, ha
de-reisha shamat mina, one minute, that's implicit in the beginning of the
משנה. Mishnah. הייתה כתובתה מאתיים ומכרה שווה מנה במאתיים, Haita kesubatah masayim
u-machra shaveh maneh be-masayim, it was worth 200 and she sold 100
for 200, so then okay, she's paid off because she pocketed 200.
או שווה מאתיים במנה, O shaveh masayim be-maneh, or 200 for 100,
נתקבלה כתובתה, nitkabla kesubatah,
she's been paid off. So you see that when she undersells it
but basically the loss can go to paying off, to be deducted
from the debt, it's a valid sale.
גמרא Gemara says no, מהו דתימא התם הוא דאסתלק לה מהאי ביתא
לגמרי. mahu d'teima hatam hu de-istalkat lah me-hai beita legamre. That's when
after that sale she's done. She's totally paid off and she just
walks away. Okay, then you could say look, it was worth 200,
you take the hit, we're done. אבל הכא, Aval hacha, but here,
when it was 125 and she sold it for 100, okay, I
might say that even if that was one of the מנה maneh
guys she was selling to, right? She sold to three guys for
100 and the last guy for 125. So let's say she sold
to a middle guy 125 for 100. Then we would say, okay,
you take the hit, you only pocketed 100 but we're going to
deduct 125 from the outstanding debt. That's what we would say. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, I might have thought that we wouldn't
do that. Why not? ניגזור מנה ראשון אטו מנה אחרון. Nigzor maneh
rishon atu maneh acharon. If we say that in the middle when
she undersells we're going to deduct the actual value from the debt,
maybe I won't let that debt be valid because then we'll come
to say the same thing when she sells to the last guy
and she undersells and then it shouldn't be valid. So קמשמע לן
kamashma lan that we will let it be valid. So there's like
three cases here, it's getting a little confusing. Yeah, I'm going to
say it again. Okay, and then go, go to Rachel's question, I'm
not ignoring you Rachel.
Just want to get my point through, okay?
There are basically three cases in the משנה. Mishnah. One is she
sold it here, it's worth when she sold it. So in the
first case of the משנה, Mishnah, and here's her outstanding כתובה. Kesubah.
Okay, so in the first case of the משנה Mishnah is her
outstanding כתובה Kesubah is 200, it was worth 200 and she sold
it for 100, okay? So she undersold it. Okay, and we say
that the כתובה Kesubah is paid off, that she takes the hit.
Okay,
she takes the hit. Okay,
that basically the כתובה Kesubah is paid off. That was one case.
Okay, then the case we're trying to figure out was the case
where her כתובה Kesubah was 100
and it was and here's the question, she sold it for 125.
Okay, no wait, the other way. Yeah, no, the other way. It
was worth, wait, yeah, it was worth 125. And we're trying to
figure out what the case was. Is that what we're talking about?
Is the case that we're talking about that she sold it for
a hundred and twenty-five and the הלכה Halacha is that it's void?
Okay, but is the case that she sold it for a hundred
and twenty-five or is the case that she sold it for a
hundred? If the case is she sold it for a hundred and
twenty-five, saying she's void is saying that a שליח Shaliach who oversteps,
okay,
is
it's you know he's not being a שליח, Shaliach, okay? It's void.
That would be what that says because she overstepped. She was only
supposed to have sold for a hundred, right? She sold something worth
too much. You get that? She didn't undersell, point was that she
overstepped what her you know what she was entitled to be doing.
If the meaning of the משנה Mishnah is it was a hundred
and twenty-five and she sold for a hundred, then the point is
that if you undersell it's void. Okay, now how is saying it's
undersell void different than here when it's undersell it's valid? Because it
works. Because here, no, because here, no why does it work here
and why is it void here? Okay, and the reason is because
here, here the result's not getting a hit. Fine, so here she
yes she undersold but she'll take the hit. We'll use the actual
value, what she should have gotten for it to pay off her
כתובה. Ketubah. Here the estate is taking the hit. If the estate
is taking the hit, then because the actual value, right, of it,
they can't say fine we'll deduct it from your כתובה. Ketubah. There's
no כתובה Ketubah left to pay. Okay, so that was case number
two. And case number three was, okay, a hundred, she had a
כתובה Ketubah for four hundred.
There was worth, I mean,
and then there were cases of a hundred, a hundred, a hundred,
a hundred and twenty-five, okay? And she sold it for a hundred,
a hundred, a hundred and then a hundred. So this last case,
right, is void. And the reason it's void is because it was
undersold and it was undersold and she can't, there's nothing, and wait
wait no I'm sorry, yeah it's undersold and there's she, the estate
has to take the hit, not her, because she only has a
hundred left of her כתובה Ketubah to be paid off, right? Undersold
and the estate takes the hit. Is that clear? Yes?
Estate takes the hit. So therefore it's void.
Okay, well why can't you say she take the hit? It's void,
she gives them back twenty-five. What? Why can't you say?
No, no, no, she, whatever, the משנה, Mishnah, it's only if it
automatically gets deducted from her כתובה. Ketubah. I mean the משנה Mishnah
talks about why she can't offer to take it back or whatever,
but then like they don't have to want to worry about that.
We wanted the piece of land, we didn't want this, whatever. If
you basically are entitled to be selling it and you undersold it,
you just hurt yourself in the process, but fundamentally you were entitled
to be selling it. Okay, so basically what the גמרא Gemara is
saying is like this: is that if the case of our משנה
Mishnah is this case, that if it's undersold it's void, okay, that
it says well that's different than here, here it's undersold it's okay
if you take the hit. So this is a חידוש Chiddush that
it's saying but if it's undersold and you're and she's not taking
the hit then it's void. But it says but we have over
here that if it's undersold and she's not taking the hit it's
void. So again it's redundant. So the גמרא Gemara says no. Here
it's a difference of, here's a difference that if, wait a minute,
did I get it confused right now?
Oh, I'm sorry, bless you. So the גמרא Gemara says that, I'm
sorry. So the גמרא Gemara says, ah, there's a חידוש Chiddush is
about the middle cases. Here it's undersold, I'm sorry, the חידוש Chiddush
is the middle cases, right? Here it's undersold and she takes the
hit.
I'm sorry, now I lost my train of thought. One minute. אטו
Atu middle,
the line is explained as the קא משמע לן. Ka mashma lan.
Got it. אטו מכר קיים, Atu mecher kaiam, right? אמי רישא שמע
מינה? Ami reisha shma mina? סיפא, Seifa, הא קא משמע לן Ha
ka mashma lan דאידי דלא בדיעתא דמי. d'eidi d'lo bideiata demi. Right.
Okay, yeah.
So
it's only by inference. The גמרא Gemara is saying like this: the
חידוש Chiddush here of this end case is that it's only void
because the estate took the hit. If earlier on she had sold
it for a hundred and twenty-five, right? I mean she sold for
a hundred and twenty-five part of it for a hundred. If she
had sold something for a hundred that was worth a hundred and
twenty-five for a hundred, okay, that would be good but she would
take the hit, right? So the גמרא Gemara is saying well we
see that here. That if it's good she takes the hit, it's
void. But no. Here it's good because after, after she sold it,
she's paid off and she leaves. If we let this sale be
good and said you take the hit, then we would say wait
wait maybe we shouldn't allow that because if we let a middle
sale, where there's still an outstanding debt, be good as long as
she takes the hit, then in the final sale when she's finished
paying off her debt, she might come to oversell it even though
there's no hit for her to take. Okay? So therefore we needed
to give that hit. It was very complicated. But the basic point
is I hope clear that if she takes the hit it's good.
I see Simon, you had a question from a while ago. Wait,
so the woman doesn't have an incentive to undersell the property? Correct.
Right, it's only going to hurt her. Correct. Why aren't we protecting
her from
that and making that a void sale?
Well,
you can't protect people from their own idiocy, right, or whatever. I
mean, how much is a court going to go ahead and void
every sale that somebody makes that's a bad deal?
But essentially protecting the estate and the heirs.
I understand. So we, I mean, basically what you're saying is why
don't we just institute laws of אונאה בקרקע ona'ah b'karka all the
time, so anytime anybody buys or sells property that they feel was
under or over sold, we're going to void it?
No, I'm saying that there
seems to be a desire to protect
the
estate at the expense of the woman.
Nobody's being, no, no, no, it's not like some preference. I don't
see any of this being about a preference. I think somebody has
license or power to do something to sell off their debt, but
they can't do it in a way that hurts another, you know,
hurts another party. Who are we, who are we preferencing here? Why
are we preferencing anybody? If you go ahead and you take my
property and you undersell it, right, so you've done essentially injury to
my property, right? That's not preferencing me over you. You know, you
actually did to me a financial injury. So you should be the
one to suffer. You walk into my shop and you, and you
bang into something and you break it, you pay it because, not
because we're preferencing me, because it's just my property you're protecting, right?
So that's all that's happening here. If you go ahead and take
a field worth 200 and you went ahead and you undersold it,
why should I be the one to suffer? It was your, it
was your negligence essentially.
The line that I think you were explaining now, which I still
don't understand, is דחזי ליה למנה ראשונה ולא למנה אחרונה,
dechazi leh lemana rishona v'lo
lemana achrona,
which we don't say כמאן דאמר. k'man d'amar.
Right, I would have said that what the Gemara is saying is
that the חידוש chidush of this last case, because obviously we know
if you undersell the estate takes the hit, it's not binding, that's
what we're saying here, thank you, the חידוש chidush here is that
if it was a middle case, 125 for 100, we would say
good and she takes the hit, right? That's מנה ראשונה. mana rishona.
If it's somewhere in the middle.
Okay, if it's somewhere in the middle, we say that's fine, there's
an outstanding debt, it's a binding sale, she takes the hit. But
I know here that if it's an, if there's enough money of
her debt to cover it, it's good and she takes the hit.
It says no, no, no, here, okay, she takes the hit and
then we're done. But here, if she takes the hit and we
say it's good, deduct it from the outstanding debt, then when she
gets down here, she might over sell again and then there's no
hit for her to take. I got that. So that's מנה ראשונה.
mana rishona. We shouldn't let the מנה ראשונה mana rishona be binding
because it will lead to making the מנה אחרונה mana achrona binding.
And that's what נגזור nigzor means? Why don't we make a גזירה
gezeirah to prevent this case from being binding? Why don't we make
a גזירה gezeirah to void this case? Because if we allowed this
case to be binding and say the heirs are protected because she's
taking the hit, it's going to lead to this case.
קא משמע לן
ka
mashma lan that we don't think that, that we allow this to
be good because it's still good, she takes the hit, and this,
if it ever happens, will be bad because then there's no hit
for her to take.
So we admit that middle case, we don't? We do.
That's the חידוש. chidush. The חידוש chidush is that
only the last case is no good because then there's no hit
for her to take. Ah, we don't disallow the earlier sale because
it could lead to an impropriety with the end. Exactly. Got it.
All right, let's move on. Okay, yeah, it could lead to,
it could lead
to the מנה אחרונה.
mana achrona. We don't totally void the whole.
All right. איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, others say. I did not realize
those ten lines were going to be that hard. איכא דאמרי. ika
d'amri.
Well, there was only one line.
All right. הא לא צריכא לך. ha la tzricha lach. This question
of when a שליח shaliach oversteps his bounds, or I should say
her, my god, I'm talking about a woman, I'd better as well
say her. When a שליח shaliach oversteps her bounds, that we're not
asking. היכא דאמר ליה זיל זבון לי לתכא, heicha d'amar leh zil
zvun li letka, a guy says, go sell for me a half
an acre. וזבין ליה כורא, v'zavin leh kora, and he sells an
acre. דבמאי מוסיף על דבריו הוי. d'vavai mosif al d'varav havay. Then
certainly what he's doing is he's doing his agency. Notice the he,
I kept, right, went back to the he. Certainly what she's doing
is she's doing her agency, the first part, and the part that
she oversteps, then she's acting on her own, but she's not acting
on her own for the whole thing. For the part that she
was, you know, empowered to do, she's still doing. So if the
woman went ahead and sold 125 for 125, if that was the
case, actually it would be binding. Okay, that we'd take for granted,
right? So that the part that she is empowered for. is binding,
and it's only the part that she overstepped that's an overstep. But
it's not מעביר על דבריו, maavir al devaro, it's not fundamentally going
rogue. That's if she overstepped. That case we would say is not
going rogue, at least for the overlap part. Okay, דברי מוסיף על
דבריו הוי. devarai mosif al devaro havei. He's saying, look, I'm a
מוסיף mosif as opposed to מעביר. maavir. מוסיף mosif means A plus
X. The hundred part that was the agency. The extra 25, that
was my own thing. As opposed to מעביר maavir that the whole
thing is stepping out of bounds. Okay, so that would be a
binding שליחות shlichus for the base amount. הכי בעיא לך, Hechi baia
lach, what am I asking? דאמר ליה de'amar lei that again because
the גמרא Gemara is in the masculine. He said to him, זיל
זבין לי כורא, zil zavin li kura, go and buy for me
an acre, ואזל וזבין ליה לתכא. ve'azal vezavin lei leticha. I'll make
it she. She went and bought a half-acre. מאי, Mai, what do
we say in that case, when she did less than she was
appointed, not more than she was appointed? מי אמרינן, Mi amrinan, אמר
ליה, amar lei, דטבא לך עבדי לך. detava lach avdi lach. The
שליח shaliach can say to the person who sent her, I did
for you, I benefited you. How did I benefit you? אי לא
מצטרכת לזוזי, ei lo mitztarchet lezuzei,
because if in the end you're not going to need that cash,
לא מצטרכת הדרת ביה. lo mitztarchet hadrat bei. The assumption here is
that if people are selling the land, land is the primary source
of wealth here, and
nobody sells it unless they are very hard up and need cash
to pay off debts. Okay, you don't, nobody was in a business
of flipping properties in order to make money. All right. So therefore,
if somebody says go sell me this piece of land, it's because
they have outstanding debts, they're in financial crisis, they need it sold.
So the שליח shaliach comes back and says I sold half for
half of the amount you needed. Look, I'm doing you a favor,
because it might be that you'll be able to push off the
creditors, you'll be able to whatever, pay off the rest of debt
without having to sell the rest of the land. If it winds
up you need to sell the rest of the land, we could
always go back and sell the other half. Okay, so therefore, even
though I did less than you asked for, it still is ultimately
in your interest and I should be considered to be operating still
on your behalf. So it's interest, right? When I did exactly what
you asked for, not exactly, when I did what you asked for
plus, since there was that overlap that I did 100% of what
you asked, the גמרא Gemara says then you are a שליח. shaliach.
But if you did 50% of what you asked for, you can't
say, well, the only argument that you're still a שליח shaliach in
that capacity has to be an argument about why ultimately it was
in your best interests, right? In some objective way you can't just
say, well, you said 100, you did 50, 50 is included in
100. No, if it wasn't the whole thing then it's considered that
fundamentally you didn't do what I asked for, unless you can make
an argument that no, ultimately this really was in your best interest.
And that argument somehow seems to say that I'm still operating as
your agent. And here's the argument, of course he'd say, buddy, let
me decide what's in my best interest, I'm the one that appointed
you. Okay, so that's an interesting question. Do you need this argument
that you can say bottom line this really is better for you,
or do we just say no, if I say 100 and you
did 50, 100 includes 50, so in that 50 you were still
my agent or not?
Okay, so here's the argument, I did you a favor by only
selling half of your field, right, because you could come into the
cash in another week or two, and if I would have sold
the whole thing and you'd come into the cash you wouldn't have
been able to ask for half the field back.
Exactly, exactly. Okay, ואיכא דאמרי, Ve'ika de'amrei,
or do we say, אמר ליה, amar lei, he could say to
me, לא ניחא לי דליפוש שטרי עלואי. lo nicha li delipush shetarei
ilavai. I don't want there to be a lot of documents against
me. Now it's funny, a document against me
presumably means when people have debts against me. Okay, but here documents,
what does he mean, documents of sale?
It sounds like it means I don't want to have two sales,
but maybe again, maybe we have to put ourselves in their mindset.
If people are only selling to pay off debts and you have
a history of selling a lot of land, it's like a bad
credit history, right, where selling a lot of land shows that you
have a lot of debts to pay off. So if you've only
had one bad, right, I assume for your credit history if you've
had like 10 times you've defaulted on a whatever on a whatever,
been late or whatever on a thousand dollars, it's worse than once
ten thousand and then paying it off, right? Like there's a repeated
pattern.
Maybe it's the רמב"ם, Rambam, I'll give him credit.
I don't know, I assume that there's a problem of a repeated
pattern, I'm guessing. Anyway, so that's what he says, I'm sorry, I
don't want to start establishing this pattern of multiple sales. Of course,
you could also say other things, you know, you could maybe get
a better deal by selling a large piece of land than two
partial pieces of land. There's a lot of reasons why it wouldn't
be in his interest. Okay, so what do we say when you
underdo? So now again the way the גמרא Gemara is framing it,
it's a very specific question to the sale of land and the
specific considerations around the sale of land. But we could have asked
it in a more abstract way about when you underdo what you
were asked, were you still being an agent for the part that
you were doing? And the גמרא Gemara is now going to abstract
it. Although it made it very concrete and specific about land, it's
now going to abstract the question.
But no, let's get a little further. This looks like לשון של
נפש. Lashon shel nefesh.
Yes, a lot. אמר רבי חנינא מסורא, Amar Rabi Chanina Misura, תא
שמע, Ta shema, come hear. נתן
לו דינר של זהב, natan lo dinar shel zahav, back to מעילה,
Meilah, that's a great example of testing whether somebody is a שליח.
shaliach. You gave your שליח shaliach a golden דינר, dinar, ואמר לו,
ve-amar lo, הביא לי חלוק, havi li chaluk, okay, and go buy
me a shirt. And basically this דינר dinar was הקדש, Hekdesh, and
you and your שליח shaliach didn't realize that it was sanctified. Go
buy me a shirt.
והלך והביא לו בשלוש חלוק ובשלוש טלית. Ve-halach ve-heivi lo be-shalosh chaluk
u-ve-shalosh talit. And he went and brought with three סלע, sela, three
סלע sela is a half of a דינר, dinar, okay? So it's
a little confusing that it switches the coinage. But anyway, he went
ahead and he bought with half of the דינר dinar a shirt,
and with the other half of the דינר dinar he bought a
טלית, talit, a like a cloak, okay? So, טלית talit here does
not mean a ritual טלית. talit. Okay, anyway, so what's the הלכה?
halacha? שניהם מעלו. Shneihem ma'alu. They both did מעילה. meilah. Why did
they both do מעילה? meilah? For the buying of a shirt, he
was doing my שליחות. shlichut. For the buying of the טלית, talit,
I never asked him to do that, he was acting on his
own, and therefore he misused הקדש, Hekdesh, and I didn't. So what
do you see? You see though for the buying of the shirt,
I told him to buy
a six סלע sela shirt, and he bought a three סלע sela
shirt, so he's still considered to be acting on my behalf. Okay,
and that's a real difference, like a three סלע sela shirt is
not the same as a six סלע sela shirt. One's to sell
half the amount of land, right? You still sold that and you
got the proceeds, and the other half is waiting to be sold.
It's another thing, right, to go ahead and to buy a shirt
that's worth half as much. It's not the same shirt, okay? It's
not like I could always buy the other half, another shirt for
three סלע sela and put them together and get the shirt I
want. Okay, so let's take a look. And nevertheless it says that
he is my שליח. shaliach. Okay, so it says like
this, שניהם מעלו. shneihem ma'alu. So אי אמרת בשלמא שליח כהאי גוונא
עושה שליחותו
ומוסיף על דבריו הוי. I amarta bishlama shaliach ke-hai gavna oseh shlichuto
u-mosif al devarav havei. If you say that in that case a
שליח shaliach is considered to have done his שליחות, shlichut, okay and
basically his שליחות shlichut when he bought the three shekel, the three
סלע sela shirt, and then when he bought the טלית talit he
was going off and acting on his own. Okay, so משום הכי
בעל הבית מעל. mishum hachi ba'al ha-bayit ma'al.
That's why the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayit did מעילה meilah for the
three shekel סלע sela shirt. אלא אי אמרת מעביר על דבריו הוי,
Ela im amarta ma'avir al devarav havei,
if when he does less he actually is acting rogue, he's going
against the whole שליחות, shlichut, so אמאי מעל? amai ma'al? Why did
I do מעילה? meilah? When he bought the shirt, he was not
acting on my behalf, he was doing his own thing. Why did
the
בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayit do מעילה? meilah? הכא במאי עסקינן דאייתית ליה
שוה שש בשלוש. Hacha be-mai askinan de-ayteit lei shaveh sheisha be-shalosh. No,
because what the שליח shaliach did is, he went to a bargain
basement or whatever the store, and he got a sale. And he
got you the six סלע sela shirt for three סלע. sela. And
he had money left over. So therefore he was totally acting on
your behalf, he bought you the object you wanted, and he saved
you money.
Okay, so he should have given you the savings
instead of going and buying a טלית. talit. Right. So the savings
he should have given you, he went and he bought a טלית,
talit, then he was acting on his own. But in the buying
of the shirt, he totally did you a favor and he did
exactly what you wanted. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, אי הכי בשליח אמאי מעל? i hachi bi-shaliach amai ma'al? So
why did he מועל moel with the extra money? Because again, if
he saved you money and got you what you wanted then he
seems to be doing a good thing for you. No, a טלית.
talit. No, when he bought the טלית, talit, even though you know
that was all
windfall, maybe less. Nevertheless, you never said you wanted a טלית, talit,
and there he was acting on his own.
So it's not like he got you.
That's not too bad. אי הכי i hachi says the גמרא, Gemara,
אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the end. רבי יהודה אומר
אף בזה בעל הבית לא מעל. Rabbi Yehuda omer af be-zeh ba'al
ha-bayit lo ma'al. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said, no, even in this
case of the שליח shaliach buying
a three סלע sela shirt, the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayit was not
מועל. moel. Why? מפני שיכול לומר לו, mipnei she-yachol lomar lo, he
could say back to the שליח, shaliach, חלוקא דבעינא ליה שגיא ומעליא
ואייתית לי חלוקא קטינא ורע. chaluka di-veina lei sagi u-ma'alya ve-ayteit li
chaluka katina ve-ra.
I wanted a nice big one and you bought me a small,
bad one. So now that sounds like he bought one that was
worth three סלע. sela. I wanted a good six סלע sela one
and he bought one that was worth three סלע. sela. So there
it actually seems as a debate between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is exactly our question. I told him
to get a six סלע sela one, he bought one that was
half as good. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says he's still my
שליח shaliach and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says he's not your שליח,
shaliach, he got you something very different than you wanted. That's what
it sounds like. But so the גמרא Gemara says if you want
to say that otherwise, you want to say that the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma is saying that he got you a sale, he got
you a bargain, so what's bothering רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, מאי רע? mai ra? So what does
it mean bad? What's bad? He got you exactly what you wanted.
No, רע בדמים. ra be-damim. No, he didn't make as much, he
didn't get as good of a bargain as he could have.
Meaning I wanted him to spend six סלע sela on a shirt,
he should have used the whole six סלע sela and got me
even a better shirt. Okay, so אמר ליה, amar lei, he should
have... It was on sale. I know, whatever, that's what the גמרא
Gemara says. It's not like we have now some clothes are marked
down, some are not. You go to the tailor presumably and if
you... I don't know, גמרא Gemara assumed that everything would have been
on sale. דאייתית לי בשש. di-ayteit li be-sheisha. Wait, if you'd have
sent the whole six, כל שכן דהוי שוי תריסר, kol shekein de'havei
shavei tereisar, you could have got me something worth twelve. So okay,
so anyway,
so the simple sense of what's going on here is exactly our
debate. He got you something less than you wanted. The תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma says he's your שליח, shaliach, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
you're not a שליח. shaliach. The גמרא Gemara reframes it and says
you got you what you wanted, but he got it to you
on sale. So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says okay, he's your
שליח, shaliach, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no because if it
was on sale, then you should have got something even better.
But you could get two for six.
איכא נמי דקתני, ika nami de'katani, we can also infer that from
what the משנה Mishnah says, oh, it says it's a ברייתא, Beraita,
מודה רבי יהודה בקטנית ששניהם מעלו. modei Rabbi Yehuda be'kitnis she'shneihem ma'alu.
He agrees—what? I'm summarizing. Yes, I was trying home point.
I was trying to summarize the take-home point. The take-home point is
that we are saying if I tell somebody to do something and
they do it and they do more than they were assigned to
do, then we're willing to assume that in the part that they
did that was equal to what they were assigned to do, they
were acting of my agency. The other would not. I tell them
to sell me to sell to sell buy
or to buy or to sell, whatever, to sell a plot of,
you know, a hundred dollars worth of my land and they sold
a hundred and twenty-five worth of my land. So the hundred part
is binding, the extra twenty-five is not binding. Okay, so the part
that they did what was exactly what I wanted was binding, the
extra part they're acting on their own. It's possible to subdivide. I
mean, not every case you can split like that, but anyway. If,
however, they did less than I asked them to do, I told
them to sell a hundred a plot of land worth a hundred
an acre of land and they sold a half-acre of land, that's
the question. Is it binding for that half-acre or not? Okay, that's
the question where they did less, are they operating still as my
agent or not? And the גמרא Gemara is says we have a
debate here by the guy I sent to buy a shirt for
six and he bought a shirt for three. And it seems like
there's a debate whether he was acting as my agent or not.
The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says yes and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says no because he bought you a cheap shirt, not a nice
shirt. Question, it sounds like that's exactly the debate we're asking when
somebody does less than I ask. Notice by the way it's now
not about קרקע karka and about sela and bad credit, it's a
more generic question. When somebody did a debt when somebody did less
than I asked, is he my שליח shaliach or not? That sounds
like the debate. And the גמרא Gemara wants to say no, maybe
everybody would say that he is not my שליח shaliach when he
does less. And here the case is that it was on sale,
so he actually did what I asked. He got me the nice
shirt, okay? And that's why it's good. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says the reason it's not good, even if it was on sale,
then I want would have wanted him to not have just got
a six סלע sela shirt, I would have wanted him to spend
the whole six סלע sela and get the best shirt possible, right?
So here is the debate. When I told him to get a
six סלע sela shirt, I don't know fine, when I told him
to get a six סלע sela shirt, spend six סלע sela and
get me a shirt, was I fundamentally interested in the six סלע
sela shirt? So if he spent three סלע sela on it, or
did I fundamentally want to spend six סלע sela and get the
best shirt that you can? And that's the sort of the debate.
I feel like there is an ironic there's irony here. Okay. And
the irony is you can't get it right. That this kind of
transaction between a שליח shaliach and someone else,
there's something lost in the translation always, there's always ambiguity in the
way that you execute something as an agent. That's what you're going
to do the best or you're going to really help? Yeah.
You
should have gone to the store and gotten it on sale, right,
you'd say.
Right. I mean it's a good point, you know, if you make
it too precise, then then you can't make it too precise. On
the other hand, you can't give it too much latitude either, right?
Because then he can go ahead and you know spend a lot
of my money or sell a lot of my land.
And that's inherent in the in the
transaction that there is an inequality in the in the buying and
selling.
It's always something.
It's a really it's a really good point. But you know, but
it doesn't but we have to figure out then how to strike
the balance, right?
What do the people want?
Ah, that I don't know.
What the שליח shaliach is supposed to be is a total extension
of personhood. I'm a little girl, I go to my mom and
say, what can I do for you today? I'm seven
and nine. How responsible? If you can't figure out what I need,
you can do nothing.
There you go.
And I really think we're talking about the same thing, that this
person in all good intention is trying to—well,
that's a good question.
The guy might be paid to do this stuff.
Well, we're not being told that, are we?
All right, but that's not relevant one way or the other. We're
concerned whether the sale is binding. What why he's doing it, because
he likes the guy and wants to curry favor, whether he's being
paid, whatever, that's really not our interest. But I do think that
the question is correct. Like, you know, it's all very nice hypothetically
to say you can't do more, you can't do less, but then
like, you know, as we as anybody knows who's gone shopping for
a spouse or something like that, you can never get it exactly
right. You have to use judgment. So that's the question. But I
think what I would say, what I would say, Rachel, is what
what we're getting out of this is trying to determine like what
are the limits to that? You know, I mean we don't have
a precise answer. But exactly the גמרא Gemara exactly is trying to
sort of
acknowledge— Alright so let's try to get let's try to move forward.
Okay.
Right. So anyway so it says so רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* though
says I would agree to the case not when you bought him
a cheaper shirt but when you actually were told to buy קטניות
*kitnios* legumes and you bought half as much because there you didn't
get something worse it was just a quantity issue
okay. Talking about overstepping you know this happens every single day when
I go shopping no not when I go shopping the day before
anyway but when I go shopping for the home because Adora and
I have very different approaches to shopping. She like buys pretty much
exactly what she needs. I figure like I don't want to like
if I'm out here who wants to go for the next two
weeks and just buy the stuff, stock it up, we have the
room, whatever. No that's great
so what'd you come up with exactly four potatoes? Well with me
it's the exact opposite it's where are we gonna keep all this
stuff we don't have room in the fridge you don't need all
this stuff around. So anyway so it'll go bad. Okay so that's
exactly this example.
I got you a second fridge.
So anyway so my example is so everybody who buys too much
everybody in this room who buys too much is the שליח shliach
*shaliach* who's מוסיף על דבריו *mosif al devarav* and everybody who buys
too little is the שליח shliach *shaliach* who עובר על דבריו *over
al devarav* and the question is you know does your spouse think
you did what they asked you to do or not? Okay so
anyway so let's take a look. Okay שקטניות בסלע וקטניות בפרוטה *shekitnios
besela vakitnios beperuta*. When it comes to legumes legumes you know it
goes for a סלע *sela* legumes go for a פרוטה *peruta* meaning
it's different legumes it's all just a question of quantity. Right but
it's the same case? You told him to get legumes and he
got half as much so in that case everybody agrees that in
the first half he's doing your שליחות *shlichus* because of course he
did what you wanted and it's not a different type of a
thing you have to go back to the store and buy more
but at least that there's an overlap but at least that that
case so when you're doing less so the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis*
and the both he's מוסיף על הפחת *mosif al hapachat*. Okay שמע
מינה *shema mina* so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says so somehow we
see that that indicates I don't know it's רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* is
a complicated explanation how that indicates that we're talking about what we
our issue about about a shirt being on sale rather than the
issue about קטניות *kitnios*. It's complicated how רש"י *Rashi* reads that in
because it's just as easily could have explained the case that like
we said that they're debating the case where you bought a cheap
shirt and רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* says a cheap shirt you didn't
do what they asked for if you bought too few apples or
pears you did what they asked for because at least that amount
was right so you there was more for you to buy but
at least that amount was right so there you are being a
שליח shliach *shaliach*. But when it was a different type of a
thing that's a different story but what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
trying to do is that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is trying to
to say that the case of the shirt was a case about
being on sale and what he did wrong was he didn't take
greater advantage of the sale and then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
oh you can see that because רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* concedes in
the case of the קטניות *kitnios*. How that's related to taking advantage
of the sale is not clear we're just going to move on.
Okay היכי דמי *heichei dami* what's the case? אילימא דאתא דמזבני בשומא
*ieima de'ata demizbeni beshuma* if it were the case where they sold
the food by estimate they didn't exactly weigh it out yeah looks
like whatever a you know it looks like ten dollars worth. So
היכא דיהב ליה סלע מוזיל גביה סלע *heicha deyehav leh sela mozil
gabei sela*? So we're back to the issue if we think the
issue is for רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* and תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*
whether you should have taken more advantage of the sale so is
why would he concede by the case of קטניות *kitnios*? If things
were on sale and it's all done by a rough estimate then
if you would have given in more money right then he would
have gotten a better deal you would have taken more advantage of
the sale. So אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Pappa* באתרא דכיילי בכני
*be'asra dechayilei bekanei* it's a place where they measure it out you
know in small amounts meaning that it's a very precise and it's
not estimated. דאמר ליה קנה קנה בפרוטה *de'amar leh kaneh kaneh beperuta*
every single little grain costs a פרוטה *peruta*. So therefore there's no
estimate it's very precise and in that type of a case again
the simple sense here is that in that type of a case
you did it you did half of what you asked for but
that half was still correct and you're still a שליח shliach *shaliach*
because it's all just a question of quantity. The גמרא Gemara's *Gemara*
somehow reading it that in that case there was no greater benefit
that you could have gotten in terms of making you know taking
advantage of the sale by buying more and therefore that's why רבי
יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* concedes but when there was a case where it's
not exactly clear why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* thinks that that's related
how much benefit you could have gotten out of the sale. But
when you could have taken more advantage of the sale that's how
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s reading it that's the debate. So where we
are is the following okay it seems clear that if it's just
a question of quantity and you bought half then you know okay
at least then you are doing your שליחות *shlichus* for that amount.
If it's not a question of quantity like selling a field and
there's real consequence to selling half a field as opposed to selling
a whole field or buying a shirt and buying the wrong shirt
you know a cheaper shirt and so on then there's a real
question when you change it and it's not just a question of
quantity and you did less are you really doing what you asked
for. to
get but
you
could have
taken more advantage of, more advantage of the sale. Let's no, no,
no whatever says Michael, no, we're going to the משנה. Okay, we
have nine minutes. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: תא
שמע, Tashma, come and hear. העושה כתובתה ארבע מאות זוז מכר לזה
במנה ולזה במנה ולאחרון יפה מנה בדינר ומנה במנה. Ha'oseh ketuvatah arba
me'ot zuz, mocheir la'zeh b'maneh v'la'zeh b'maneh v'la'achron yafeh maneh b'dinar v'maneh
b'maneh. Okay, the case of a hundred, hundred, hundred, and the last
guy, a hundred and twenty-five were sold for a hundred. של אחרון
בטל ושל כולן מכרן קיים. Shel achron batel v'shel kulam machran kayam.
The last one is void. So, so what's the issue here? The
issue here is that the is that land does not have a,
hold on, let me just double check here. רש"י, one minute.
Ah,
so the question is forget the last one, why the last one
is void. You know why the last one is void. Why are
the earlier ones good? She essentially is a שליח shliach. of בית
דין Beis Din or שליח shliach of the orphan, you know, appointed
by בית דין, Beis Din, but she's a שליח shliach? of the
orphan to pay off her four hundred debt. So she should be
selling land for four hundred. We've just learned that when you sell
land, when you piecemeal it out, that's not necessarily in the interests
of the seller, okay? Because you have a lot of documents against
him, he's got the sale history, whatever. So why is it valid
when she's piecemealing out the land? She should only be allowed to
sell a four hundred, you know, dollar piece of land as a
unit. Okay. All right. So that's how that's the answer. So the
גמרא says כי הא דאמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי בקטיני, k'd'amar
Rav Sheshes brei d'Rav Idi b'katinei, they're little plots of land that
are scattered all over. There's no big plot to sell. That's the
idea. Otherwise it might be a problem. Exactly. הכא נמי בקטיני, Hacha
nami b'katinei, so that's what he says in another case here too,
its little plots of land. So the גמרא says like this: פשיטא
אמר peshita amar now,
now we move on. So now we're doing going beyond your agency
and going less than your agency where the inclination of the גמרא
is that if you go beyond your agency, the part that you
did that was equal to your agency is valid, the rest is
void. If you do less than your agency and there's a real
consequence to that, it's not just a question of quantity, but it's
really something different, a different shirt, you know, different plots of land,
multiple documents, etc. It sounds like the גמרא inclination is that it's
void in that case. Now here's another case. אמר לאחד ולא לשנים,
Amar l'echad v'lo l'shnayim, you were told 'go ahead and sell this,
sell this piece of land to someone.' I said to you know
to 'find somebody to sell this piece of land to.' And I
said 'but and don't sell it to two people.' Okay? 'Don't subdivide
it or sell it to two people.' So אמר ליה לאחד ולא
לשנים, amar leh l'echad v'lo l'shnayim, I said one person, not two
people. And if you were to break it up and sell it
to two people, it clearly would be void. But אמר ליה לאחד
סתם, amar leh l'echad stam, I just say 'sell to one person.'
And I don't say 'don't sell it to two people.' מאי, Mai,
what's the story? Now that sounds pretty similar to the case before
because if you were to sell it to two people then each
sale would be half of what I asked you to do. But
maybe I could, what about if I could sell it to two
people all at once? Okay, you know, in one moment I you
know sell to two people, maybe would that be okay? So let's
take a look. רב הונא אמר לאחד ולא לשנים, Rav Huna amar
l'echad v'lo l'shnayim, if I said one, I mean one and not
two. ורב חסדא ורבה בר רב הונא דאמרי תרוייהו, V'Rav Chisda v'Rabba
bar Rav Huna d'amri duveihu, אפילו לאחד ואפילו לשנים. afilu l'echad v'afilu
l'shnayim. No, I wouldn't mind if you sold it to two. Again,
it sounds pretty similar to the previous case. Let's see where the
גמרא goes with it. לאחד ואפילו למאה, L'echad v'afilu l'me'ah, one and
even a hundred. Okay. One doesn't mean only one, you know. It
says if I say 'one and only one, one and exactly one,'
then I mean one. If I say 'one,' well, one is not
limited to more than one. Yeah, don't sell it to some... Okay,
now I have to tell you a funny story about that afterward.
ורב חסדא ורבה בר רב הונא דאמרי תרוייהו, Rav Chisda v'Rabba bar
Rav Huna d'amri duveihu, okay, אפילו לאחד ואפילו למאה. afilu l'echad v'afilu
l'me'ah. איקלע רב נחמן לסורא. Ikla Rav Nachman l'Sura. Rav Nachman dropped
by in Sura. עול
לגבי רב חסדא ורבה בר רב הונא. Aul l'gabbei Rav Chisda v'Rabba
bar Rav Huna. Rav Chisda and Rabba bar Rav Huna you know
came in to see him. אמרו ליה, Amru leh, they said to
him, כי האי גוונא מאי, Ki hai gavna mai, what would be
the story? Somebody told a שליח shliach. 'sell this to one person'
and he sold it to two people. אמר להו לאחד ואפילו לשנים
לאחד ואפילו למאה. Amar lehu l'echad v'afilu l'shnayim l'echad v'afilu l'me'ah. Like
we said before, if he doesn't say 'not two,' then he's not
limiting it. You could sell it to two, you could even sell
it to a hundred. אמרו ליה, Amru leh, they said to him,
אף על גב דטעה שליח, Af al gav d'ta'ei shliach, so how
about, that's your question, right? So how much latitude? They're seeing that
his basic point is that he gives a certain amount of discretion
to the שליח. shliach They says, 'Well, what if the שליח actually
made a mistake? Let's say he actually undersold it. How much discretion
are you giving the שליח?' So that raised, I think, points to
your point which is, you know, the beginning of the גמרא was
very formalistic about it. Did he do less? Did he do more?
Right? And here you see the response to him is, 'Oh, so
you're giving a lot of discretion to the שליח. Would you allow
it to be binding even if the שליח made a mistake?' So
then he says ואמר להו דבטעה שליח לא קאמינא. v'amar lehu d'b'ta'ei
shliach lo ka'amina. I'm not talking about mistakes. Okay, if he undersold
it, that wouldn't be included. What would be included is things that
are not so essential. You know, a little bit more, a little
bit less, two people, one person, two people, certainly here he's got
discretion, other areas you do not have discretion. Again, how you exactly
know what it was is not clear. Okay, so the גמרא says
like this: אמרו ליה, Amru leh, they said to him, והאמר מר
אין אונאה לקרקעות. v'ha'amar mar ein ona'ah l'karka'ot. So one minute, but
we said that there is no overcharging or undercharging by land. קרקע
*karka*. So how could you say that if the שליח *shaliach* makes
a mistake, it's void? What type of mistake is there? There's no
fixed price to קרקע *karka*. Says no, הני מילי היכא דטעה בעל
הבית *hani mili heicha detah ba'al habayit*. That's when the owner over
or under sells, then that's the price you agree to. Okay, there's
no fixed price to קרקע *karka*. אבל שליח *aval shaliach*, but if
I make somebody my agent to sell it, so אמר ליה *amar
lei*, and I could say to the agent, לתקוני שדרתיך ולא לעוותי
*litkunei shidartich velo la'avutei*. I sent you for my benefit, not to
hurt me. Meaning the point is it's not the sale of the
land at too high a price is void because of overcharging. The
sale is void because I did not want—that he was going outside
of the boundaries of his agency, right? So if I was buying
or selling it, it would be binding. That's an acceptable price for
the land that's not considered overcharge. But if I send somebody to
do it for me, then I could say I didn't want—I never
would have wanted you to represent me to go ahead and undersell
it to such a degree. Now, of course you realize that now
nobody would ever therefore buy or sell land except through a שליח
*shaliach*. Okay, פשט *pshat*, because at any time you got the raw
end of the deal, you could say, 'Ah, it wasn't my שליח
*shaliach* for that.' Right? So it's like—I don't really understand why you
don't always do it that way. One minute. אמר ליה *amar lei*,
okay, now, מנא תימרא *mina teimra*, how do I know דשאני בין
שליח לבעל הבית *deshani bein shaliach leba'al habayit*, it makes a difference,
meaning something that if the owner did would be binding because it's
within a range of acceptable binding activity, but if a שליח *shaliach*
did it's not binding because he's acting outside of the agency. דתנן
*detnan*, האומר לשלוחו *ha'omer lishlucho*, you tell your messenger, your agent, צא
תרום *tzeitrom*, go ahead and take the תרומה *trumah* from the grain.
Now, תרומה *trumah* normally is a range. The normal person gives 2%,
אחד מחמשים *echad mechameishim*. A generous person gives one out of 40,
and a stingy person gives one out of 60. So תרם כדעת
בעל הבית *taram kedat ba'al habayit*, if he takes תרומה *trumah* based
on what he estimates the owner normally does. ואם אינו יודע דעתו
של בעל הבית *ve'imei lo yodea dato shel ba'al habayit*, if he
can't estimate, doesn't know what the owner normally does, תורם בבינונית *torm
bebeynonit*, he does the average, he does 1/50, 2%. אחד מחמשים *echad
mechameishim*.
פיחת עשרה או הוסיף עשרה *pihas asara o hosif asara*, if he
does 1/10 more or less, he does the—not literally 1/10—1/40 or 1/60.
Meaning the בעל הבית *ba'al habayit*—no, no, the שליח *shaliach*, the שליח
*shaliach* does the either the very generous or the very stingy ends
of edge of the normal range. תרומתו תרומה *trumato trumah*, still binding
because that's the normal range. He just—you know, you go for the
middle of the normal range, but anywhere within the normal range is
still binding. That's considered, by the way, Rachel's right, see, there's a
certain amount of latitude within a certain range you're considered to still
be operating based on the שליחות *shlichut*. Okay, but אילו גבי בעל
הבית *ilu gabei ba'al habayit*, but the owner himself, תניא *tanya*, תרם
בעל הבית אפילו אחד מעשרה *taram ba'al habayit afilu echad me'asara*, a
guy took תרומה *trumah* and he just estimated and turned out that
he was taking 5% as opposed to 2%? So he could say,
'Oh, if I'd have been 5%—if I realized how much I was
taking, I never would have taken that much.' No. תרומתו תרומה *trumato
trumah*, it's binding. Okay? If you're the guy doing it yourself, sort
of like there's no אונאה *ona'ah* by קרקע *karka*, however much you
take is binding. You can't say oh it's too much objectively.
Or the other way around. Could be even 1/100.
Well, that goes without saying. Okay, now, so you see, if the
owner himself did it, there's no reason in terms of laws of
תרומה *trumah* that it can't work to take that amount. But if
the שליח *shaliach* did it, he has to operate within the normal
range of what the owner would have wanted, and out—going outside of
that range makes it not-it. So similarly by selling land: if I
sell it, there's no fixed price, whatever I sell it for is
binding, or buy it for. But if my שליח *shaliach* does it,
he has to operate within a normal range of price, and when
you outstep that—step outside that range, it's not binding. Okay, תא שמע
*tashma*, so now we're going to end it. This question about selling
to two or three people. היתה כתובתה ארבע מאות זוז, מכרה לזה
במנה ולזה במנה ולאחרון שוה מנה בדינר, של אחרון בטל ושל כולם
מכרן קיים *hayita ktuvatah arba me'ot zuz, machra lizeh bemaneh velizeh bemaneh
vela'acharon shaveh maneh bedinar, shel acharon batul veshel kulam machran kayam*. So
you see, presumably if he only should have sold it to one
person and he sold it to four and it's still good, so
you see that you're not limited. So אמר רב ששת בריה דרב
אידי בקטיני *amar Rav Sheshet brei deRav Idi biktini*. No, no, that
was small plots of land. I know, there was a different version
of the same issue. But what's nice about the last discussion, Rachel,
you should be very happy, is that the last discussion, rather than
a formal question of exactly this, no less no more, seems to
speak more generally about a question of how much discretion do you
have, how much are you supposed to interpret what the person said
and the amount of discretion that you use. Okay. I have to
tell you a very funny story about one in a...